Collection on P. T. Barnum MS002
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Collection on P. T. Barnum
1837 -- 1985
1818 -- 2009
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Barnum, P. T. (Phineas Taylor)
MS002
10.55 Linear Feet
1 Artifact(s)
63 Digital Object(s)
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series: Correspondence, photographs, and other material; Loose prints.
Biographical / Historical
Phineas Taylor (P.T.) Barnum (1810-1891) was born in Bethel, Connecticut on July 5, 1810. He held a series of diverse jobs as a youth, including selling theater tickets. In 1835 Barnum exhibited Joice Heth, an old black woman he claimed to be the 161-year-old nurse of George Washington, at Niblo's Gardens in New York City. He then became head of a traveling company of performers, acrobats, freaks, and wild animals.
In 1840 Barnum bought and re-opened the American Museum in New York City. Exhibits included the Feegee [sic] mermaid, the bearded lady, and the "Egress," along with fossils and natural history specimens. Barnum discovered and exhibited the dwarf Tom Thumb and made several tours to England and Europe (1844, 1858). He modeled his Connecticut mansion Iranistan (destroyed by fire in 1857), in part, on the Brighton Pavilion. In 1850 Barnum brought Jenny Lind to America for a concert tour.
From 1851 to 1857 he was one of the founding trustees of the new Universalist institution, Tufts College (opened in 1854). After being elected to the Trustees in 1851, Barnum resigned in 1857, because his busy schedule of tours precluded his attendance at board meetings. In fact, the only record that exists of Barnum actually visiting the campus was in 1886 for the commencement ceremony. On the occasion of that visit the Tufts Glee Club greeted him with "The Barnum Song" composed by then-student Leo Rich Lewis, who was later to become professor of music and composer of numerous Tufts songs.
In the 1870's Barnum organized the "Greatest Show on Earth, which traveled by train through the United States and Canada. In 1881 he joined his business rivals to form the Barnum and Bailey Circus. His correspondence of this period explains that he is too busy to attend Tufts functions, such as Commencements. In 1882, Barnum bought Jumbo, then the largest known African elephant, for $10,000 from the Royal Zoological Society in London. After great protest in England, he brought the animal to America.
Between 1882 and 1884, Barnum secretly gave over $50,000 to Tufts College to build the Barnum Museum of Natural History. He also left over $30,000 in his will to build two subsequent wings. Barnum had the bodies of dead circus animals preserved and mounted by Ward's Natural Science Establishment (taxidermists) for exhibit in the museum. In 1885, Jumbo was killed by a train in Ontario, Canada. The elephant, stuffed by Carl Akeley and William Critchley, was taken on more circus tours. In 1889, Barnum donated the half of the stuffed Jumbo he owned to the Barnum Museum at Tufts, with the idea that the publicity might be useful to the college. In 1889 Barnum made his last tour to England and compiled the scrapbook of his trip which is now in the collection. Barnum died in Bridgeport, Connecticut on April 7, 1891. In April, 1975, a fire in Barnum Hall destroyed Jumbo and much other Barnumiana, including Barnum's desk, his bust, many circus posters, and some letters.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, inventories, photographs, clippings, and memorabilia documenting aspects of the career of P.T. Barnum and Barnum's relationship with Tufts University. The development and maintenance of Barnum Hall and the Barnum Museum are detailed through the correspondence of Barnum, Professor John P. Marshall, the Smithsonian Institution, and Ward's Natural Science Establishment, dating from the 1870s through the 1890s. Transcriptions of many of these letters exist. Also included are letters authored by Barnum and his contemporaries and collected by, or donated to, Tufts University. Twentieth-century correspondence is mainly authored by Russell L. Carpenter, curator of the Barnum Museum. Carpenter's drafts of manuscripts and lectures about Barnum and Jumbo are present. Inventories outlining some of the artifacts contained in the Museum date from 1856 through the 1930's. Clippings from the 19th and 20th centuries relate to Barnum's career, Jumbo the elephant's career, Jumbo's role as Tufts' mascot, the fire that destroyed Jumbo, and occasionally, circuses in general. Photographs show Barnum Hall, Barnum circus characters, and Jumbo alive, immediately following his death, and on display at Tufts. Memorabilia dates from the 19th and 20th centuries and includes Barnum's scrapbook from his 1889 London circus tour, framed drawings and clippings of Jumbo, copper plates showing an artist's representation of Jumbo's death, an elephant prod, advertising cards featuring jumbo, a "Cut-Up Jumbo" puzzle, and a segment of Jumbo's tail, removed during renovation of the stuffed elephant. Materials in the P. T. Barnum Collection were both generated and collected by Tufts University. Interfiled with Barnum's correspondence with Tufts are letters on unrelated topics, presumably purchased from dealers. Transcriptions of many of the earliest letters appear, both in separate folders and interfiled with the original correspondence. The bulk of the materials are not organized chronologically and it is not uncommon, particularly in folders of clippings and photographs, to find materials that span the 19th and 20th centuries in a single folder. In the 20th-century correspondence, there are interfiled letters in response to reference questions relating to the archival materials themselves. Memorabilia rounds out the collection. Within each material type, documents are frequently grouped by subject. Twentieth-century correspondence and materials relating to the maintenance of the museum and the archival collection appear at random intervals. An item level listing of letters authored by P.T. Barnum exists.
Tufts College--Board of Trustees; University history; Jumbo (Elephant); Barnum, P. T. (Phineas Taylor)
- Correspondence, photographs, and other material, 1818 -- 2009; 1818 -- 1993; MS002.001; 10.55 Linear Feet; 1 Artifact(s); 20 Digital Object(s)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Correspondence, manuscripts, inventories, photographs, clippings, and memorabilia documenting aspects of the career of P.T. Barnum and Barnum's relationship with Tufts University. The development and maintenance of Barnum Hall and the Barnum Museum are detailed through the correspondence of Barnum, Professor John P. Marshall, the Smithsonian Institution, and Ward's Natural Science Establishment, dating from the 1870s through the 1890s. Transcriptions of many of these letters exist. Also included are letters authored by Barnum and his contemporaries and collected by, or donated to, Tufts University. Twentieth-century correspondence is mainly authored by Russell L. Carpenter, curator of the Barnum Museum. Carpenter's drafts of manuscripts and lectures about Barnum and Jumbo are present. Inventories outlining some of the artifacts contained in the Museum date from 1856 through the 1930's. Clippings from the 19th and 20th centuries relate to Barnum's career, Jumbo the elephant's career, Jumbo's role as Tufts' mascot, the fire that destroyed Jumbo, and occasionally, circuses in general. Photographs show Barnum Hall, Barnum circus characters, and Jumbo alive, immediately following his death, and on display at Tufts. Memorabilia dates from the 19th and 20th centuries and includes Barnum's scrapbook from his 1889 London circus tour, framed drawings and clippings of Jumbo, copper plates showing an artist's representation of Jumbo's death, an elephant prod, advertising cards featuring jumbo, a "Cut-Up Jumbo" puzzle, and a segment of Jumbo's tail, removed during renovation of the stuffed elephant.
  Materials in the P. T. Barnum Collection were both generated and collected by Tufts University. Interfiled with Barnum's correspondence with Tufts are letters on unrelated topics, presumably purchased from dealers. Transcriptions of many of the earliest letters appear, both in separate folders and interfiled with the original correspondence. The bulk of the materials are not organized chronologically and it is not uncommon, particularly in folders of clippings and photographs, to find materials that span the 19th and 20th centuries in a single folder. In the 20th-century correspondence, there are interfiled letters in response to reference questions relating to the archival materials themselves. The collection was processed by Barbara J. Burke, ca. 1977, and it has been largely left in the order she imposed. The materials are loosely organized by type, with the earlier correspondence preceding printed matter, followed by photographs and illustrations. Memorabilia rounds out the collection. Within each material type, documents are frequently grouped by subject. Twentieth-century correspondence and materials relating to the maintenance of the museum and the archival collection appear at random intervals. An item level listing of letters authored by P.T. Barnum exists.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged by material type.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Letters by PT Barnum, 1-1[1/4], 1850 -- 1877; MS002.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Letters by PT Barnum, 1-1[2/4], 1878 -- 1885; MS002.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Letters by PT Barnum, 1-1[3/4], 1885 -- 1887; MS002.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Letters by PT Barnum 1-1[4/4], 1887 -- 1889; MS002.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Copies of letters, 1873 -- 1892; MS002.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - PT Barnum--documents 1-3, 1851; MS002.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Letters to PT Barnum 1-4[1/2], 1867 -- 1885; MS002.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Letters to PT Barnum 1-4[2/2], 1886 -- 1890; MS002.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Letters of John P Marshall 1-5, 1837 -- 1889; MS002.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Wards's Natural Science Establishment 1-6[1/2], 1883 -- 1887; MS002.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Ward's Natural Science Establishment 1-6[2/2], 1888 -- 1961; MS002.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - Ward's letters-transcriptions [1/2], 1883 -- 1886; MS002.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Ward's letters-transcriptions [2/2], 1887 -- 1893; MS002.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - Letters about PT Barnum 1-7, 1886 -- 1976; MS002.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
  - Letters about Jumbo 1-8[1/3], 1882 -- 1943; MS002.001.001.00015 (Box 1)
  - Letters about Jumbo 1-8[2/3], 1944 -- 1963; MS002.001.001.00016 (Box 1)
  - Letters about Jumbo 1-8[3/3], 1965 -- 1978; MS002.001.001.00017 (Box 1)
  - Letters about Barnum Museum 1-10[1/3], 1859 -- 1899; MS002.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Letters about Barnum Museum 1-10[2/3], 1914 -- 1939; MS002.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Letters about Barnum Museum 1-10[3/3], 1939 -- 1966; MS002.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - Barnum Museum collection inventories 1-11[1/4], 1857 -- 1869; MS002.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - Barnum Museum collection inventories1-11[2/4], 1872 -- 1892; MS002.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Barnum Museum collection inventories 1-11[3/4], 1872 -- 1930; MS002.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - Barnum Museum collection inventories 1-11[4/4], 1856 -- 1888; MS002.001.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - Barnum Museum documents 1-11A, 1883 -- 1889; MS002.001.002.00008 (Box 2)
  - Letters-Jenny Lind 1-12, 1848 -- 1892; MS002.001.002.00009 (Box 2)
  - Letters about Barnum Museum- Lambert Wing 1-13[1/3], 1932 -- 1934; MS002.001.002.00010 (Box 2)
  - Letters about Barnum Museum- Lambert Wing 1-13[2/3], 1934; MS002.001.002.00011 (Box 2)
  - Letters about Barnum Museum, Lambert Wing 1-13[3/3], 1935 -- 1936; MS002.001.002.00012 (Box 2)
  - Letters about circus 1-14, 1883 -- 1967; MS002.001.002.00013 (Box 2)
  - Letters about bust of Barnum 1-15, 1943 -- 1969; MS002.001.002.00014 (Box 2)
  - Old correspondence [Barnum Museum] 2-2[1/2], 1922 -- 1944; MS002.001.002.00015 (Box 2)
  - Old correspondence [Barnum Museum] 2-2[2/2], 1945 -- 1975; MS002.001.002.00016 (Box 2)
  - Clippings- Barnum 2-3, 1851 -- 1980; MS002.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Printed matter- Barnum 2-4[1/2], 1854 -- 1971; MS002.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Printed matter- Barnum 2-4[2/2], 1940 -- 1980; MS002.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Clippings- Jumbo 2-5[1/3], 1851 -- 1968; MS002.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Clippings- Jumbo 2-5[2/3], 1935 -- 1976; MS002.001.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - Clippings- Jumbo 2-5[3/3], 1818 -- 1978; MS002.001.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - Printed matter- Jumbo 2-6[1/3], 1935 -- 1985; MS002.001.003.00007 (Box 3)
  - Printed matter- Jumbo 2-6[2/3], 1936 -- 1975; MS002.001.003.00008 (Box 3)
  - Printed matter- Jumbo 2-6[3/3], 1886 -- 1985; MS002.001.003.00009 (Box 3)
  - Clippings -- Mrs. Tom Thumb, 1919 -- 1920; MS002.001.003.00010 (Box 3)
  - Clippings -- Barnum, 1926 -- 1927; MS002.001.003.00011 (Box 3)
  - Printed matter- Tufts, Barnum, Jumbo 2-7, 1927 -- 1975; MS002.001.004.00001 (Box 4)
  - Printed matter- Barnum Museum 2-8, 1940 -- 1975; MS002.001.004.00002 (Box 4)
  - Printed matter- Circus 2-9, 1883 -- 1965; MS002.001.004.00003 (Box 4)
  - Tom Thumb 2-10, 1845 -- 1980; MS002.001.004.00004 (Box 4)
  - Jenny Lind 2-11, 1941 -- 1977; MS002.001.004.00005 (Box 4)
  - Elephants(Bridgeport) 2-12, 1882 -- 1966; MS002.001.004.00006 (Box 4)
  - Barnum's American Museum 2-13, 1923 -- 1942; MS002.001.004.00007 (Box 4)
  - Ward's Natural Science Establishment 2-14, 1943 -- 1962; MS002.001.004.00008 (Box 4)
  - Jonas Brothers 2-15, 1949 -- 1954; MS002.001.004.00009 (Box 4)
  - Zoos and Museums 2-16, 1889; MS002.001.004.00010 (Box 4)
  - Russell Carpenter- MSS on Jumbo and Barnum 2-17, 1980 -- 1990; MS002.001.004.00011 (Box 4)
  - Lectures 2-18, 1946 -- 1962; MS002.001.004.00012 (Box 4)
  - Offerings of Barnumiana 2-19, 1939 -- 1967; MS002.001.004.00013 (Box 4)
  - Barnum Room (fund) 2-20, 1940 -- 1941; MS002.001.004.00014 (Box 4)
  - Barnum Room (fund) 2-20, 1940 -- 1941; MS002.001.004.00015 (Box 4)
  - Bridgeport- Barnum Festival 2-22, 1940 -- 1961; MS002.001.004.00016 (Box 4)
  - Bridgeport- Barnum Festival 2-21, 1966; MS002.001.004.00017 (Box 4)
  - Jumbo namesakes 2-22, 1951 -- 1956; MS002.001.004.00018 (Box 4)
    Some items are not dated
  - Smithsonian- duplicates of transcriptions, 1888 -- 1991; MS002.001.004.00019 (Box 4)
  - Invoices, requistions, purchase orders 2-23, 1941 -- 1968; MS002.001.004.00020 (Box 4)
  - Illustrations- Barnum and family, 1874 -- 1967; MS002.001.005.00001 (Box 5)
  - Illustrations- Jumbo, 1882; MS002.001.005.00002 (Box 5)
    - Jumbo in New York, 1882; MS002.001.005.00002.00001; Unknown (Box 5)
      Engravings; Elephants; People; Parades; Jumbo
  - Photographs and illustrations, Jumbo, 1882; MS002.001.005.00003 (Box 5)
    - Jumbo and trainer, 1882-06-11; MS002.001.005.00003.00001; Bierstadt, E. (Box 5)
      "Artotype." Caption on side of photograph: "The largest Elephant ever seen by mortal man, wild or in captivity."
      Elephants; People; Parks (grounds); Jumbo
  - Jumbo [photographs], 1922 -- 1935; MS002.001.005.00004 (Box 5)
  - Jumbo photographs, 1940 -- 1949; MS002.001.005.00005 (Box 5)
  - Jumbo photographs, 1952 -- 1958; MS002.001.005.00006 (Box 5)
  - Jumbo photographs, 1961 -- 1973; MS002.001.005.00007 (Box 5)
  - Jumbo photographs, 1882; MS002.001.005.00008 (Box 5)
    - Jumbo being fed by a policeman, 1882; MS002.001.005.00008.00001; Unknown (Box 5)
      Elephants; Parks (grounds); People; Policemen; photographic print; Jumbo
  - Illustrations- Barnum Museum [photographs] 3-3, 1884 -- 1950; MS002.001.005.00009 (Box 5)
  - Illustrations - Jenny Lind, 1840 -- 1900; MS002.001.005.00010 (Box 5)
  - Illustrations - Tom Thumb, 1863 -- 1941; MS002.001.005.00011 (Box 5)
  - Illustrations- Barnum Hall [photographs], 1886 -- 1944; MS002.001.005.00012 (Box 5)
  - Illustrations- Barnum Hall [photographs] 3-4[2/4], 1925 -- 1947; MS002.001.005.00013 (Box 5)
  - Illustrations- Barnum Hall [phtographs] 3-4[4/4], 1886 -- 1939; MS002.001.005.00014 (Box 5)
  - Barnum Museum- photgraphic negatives, 1880 -- 1920; MS002.001.005.00015 (Box 5)
  - Memorabilia 3-12, 1890; MS002.001.005.00016 (Box 5)
  - Exhibits 3-11, 1954 -- 1961; MS002.001.005.00017 (Box 5)
  - Music 3-10, 1901 -- 1943; MS002.001.005.00018 (Box 5)
  - Iranistan 3-9, 1849; MS002.001.005.00019 (Box 5)
  - Barnum Hall, 1915 -- 1965; MS002.001.005.00020 (Box Shared 35)
    This photograph was found uncatalogued in the stacks in summer 2007.
  - Jumbo in Barnum Hall, 1900 -- 1965; MS002.001.005.00021 (Box Shared 35)
  - Jumbo restoration; John Jonas, Louis Koster, and Louis Paul Jonas with Russell L. Carpenter in lab coat observing, 1942; MS002.001.005.00022 (Box Shared 36)
    Differing from that photo is the identification provided on the back. This item was found uncatalogued in the stacks in the summer of 2008.
    photographic print
  - Jumbo in Barnum Museum, 1942 -- 1943; MS002.001.005.00023 (Box Shared 36)
    Found with item 22. This photograph was found uncatalogued in the stacks in the summer of 2008.
  - Illustrations, Jumbo, 1935 -- 1950; MS002.001.006.00001 (Box 6)
  - Illustrations, Circus, 1944 -- 1962; MS002.001.006.00002 (Box 6)
  - P.T. Barnum bibliography, 1965; MS002.001.006.00003 (Box 6)
  - Elephant, Fall, 1986; MS002.001.006.00004 (Box 6)
    Article about Jumbo appears on p. 86.
    Volume, issue
    2, 2
  - American College Traditions and Customs, 1960; MS002.001.006.00005 (Box 6)
  - Jumbo Centennial coins, 1985; MS002.001.006.00006 (Box 6)
  - Jumbo Centennial narrative, exhibit list, circular, 1985; MS002.001.006.00007 (Box 6)
  - Jumbo Centennial program, 1985; MS002.001.006.00008 (Box 6)
  - Jumbo Centennial memorabilia, 1985; MS002.001.006.00009 (Box 6)
  - Information about Jumbo, 1976 -- 1994; MS002.001.006.00010 (Box 6)
  - Jenny Lind Empire Clock, 1854; MS002.001.006.00011 (Box Shared 10)
    Measures: 18" high, 13 1/2" base length, 5 1/2" base width. Inscribed with: "Presented to Mr. Phineus T. Barnum. Priscribed For By His Friends~1854~"
  - Jenny Lind Bust, 1840 -- 1870; MS002.001.006.00012 (Box Shared 10)
  - P.T. Barnum Frieze, 1830 -- 1870; MS002.001.006.00013 (Box Shared 10)
    Frieze shows P.T. Barnum and his circus, including jumbo and horse.
  - Jumbo Centennial photographs, 1985; MS002.001.006.00014 (Box Small Map Case 1 Drawer 4)
    Photographs of the Jumbo statue in St. Thomas, Ontario and the 1985 anniversity celebration of Jumbo's arrival in St. Thomas.
  - Letters from Barnum to Tufts regarding transfer of Jumbo, 1889; MS002.001.007.00001 (Box 7)
    - Letter from P.T. Barnum to John P. Marshall concerning the transfer of Jumbo, 1889; MS002.001.007.00001.00001; Barnum, P. T. (Phineas Taylor) (Box 7)
      Advertisements; Letterheads; Letters (correspondence); Barnum, P. T. (Phineas Taylor); Bailey, J. A. (James Anthony)
  - Letter form F. Elwood Smith, A1883, on the return of Jumbo to Tufts, 1890 -- 1943; MS002.001.007.00002 (Box 7)
  - Hair from Jumbo's upper lip, 1885; MS002.001.007.00003 (Box 7)
  - Descriptive placard about Jumbo, from Barnum Museum, 1930 -- 1965; MS002.001.007.00004 (Box 7)
  - Photograph of firefighter holding Jumbo's tusks, 1975; MS002.001.007.00005 (Box 7)
  - Program for the rededication of Barnum Hall, 1979; MS002.001.007.00006 (Box 7)
  - Jumbo Tin Plate, 1950 -- 1970; MS002.001.007.00007 (Box 7)
    The plate has Jumbo in the center and the alphabet around.
  - Jumbo's tail, 1885; MS002.001.008.00001 (Box 8)
    - Jumbo's tail, 2007 -- 2009; MS002.001.008.00001.00001
      Photo of Jumbo's tail taken by Jennifer Phillips for the Artifacts Exhibit in Fall, 2007
    - Jumbo's tail, 2007 -- 2009; MS002.001.008.00001.00002
    - Jumbo's tail, 2007 -- 2009; MS002.001.008.00001.00003
    - Jumbo's tail, 2007 -- 2009; MS002.001.008.00001.00004
  - Scrapbook, 1890 -- 1892; MS002.001.010.00001 (Box 10)
  - Barnum's London scrapbook, 1811 -- 1889; MS002.001.011.00001 (Box 11)
    - 'Triumphal' from Funny Folks, 1811 -- 1889; MS002.001.011.00001.00001; Unknown (Box 11)
      This image is from Barnum's London Scrapbook. Funny Folks (1874-1894) was a British newspaper comic.
      Elephants; Flags; Newspapers; Parades; People; Jumbo; Barnum, P. T. (Phineas Taylor)
  - Elephant ankus or prod, 1940; MS002.001.012.00001 (Box Shared 11)
    This was handwritten on a note attached to the ankus, "Reputed to have been used on Jumbo. Given to dad by Eugene Bowen."
  - Advertising cards, 1882 -- 1883; MS002.001.013.00001 (Box 13)
    - Advertising card featuring Jumbo drawn by spools of Willimantic thread, 1883; MS002.001.013.00001.00001; Forbes Co. Boston (Box 13)
      Advertisements; Buildings; Elephants; Horses; Parades; People; picture postcards; Jumbo
    - Advertising card featuring a caged Jumbo, 1882; MS002.001.013.00001.00002; J.H. Bufford's Sons (Box 13)
      Caption reads: "Giving Jumbo a friendly push up Broadway, N.Y., U.S.A."
    - Advertising card for spool cotton featuring Jumbo at the opera, 1883; MS002.001.013.00001.00003; Buek and Lindner (Box 13)
      Advertisements; Elephants; Operas; Opera houses; People; picture postcards; Jumbo
    - Advertising card featuring Young's birthday cards featuring Jumbo carrying children, 1883; MS002.001.013.00001.00004; J.H. Bufford's Sons (Box 13)
      Advertisements; Elephants; People; picture postcards; Jumbo
    - Advertising card featuring a caged Jumbo on a boat, 1882; MS002.001.013.00001.00005; J.H. Bufford's Sons (Box 13)
      Caption reads: "Jumbo leaving England on the way to the steamer."
      Advertisements; Boats; Elephants; Flags; People; picture postcards; Jumbo
    - Advertising card for Young's scrap books featuring Jumbo trying to escape from a cage, 1882; MS002.001.013.00001.00006; J.H. Bufford's Sons (Box 13)
      Caption reads: "Jumbo objects to being put in irons."
    - Advertising card for Kazine featuring Jumbo reaching for candy, 1882; MS002.001.013.00001.00007; J.H. Bufford's Sons (Box 13)
    - Advertising card for Castoria featuring Jumbo feeding Castoria to a baby elephant, 1883; MS002.001.013.00001.00008; Unknown (Box 13)
      The reverse of the advertising card features an advertisement for Centaur Liniment.
      Advertisements; Elephants; Parks (grounds); picture postcards; Jumbo
  - "Cut-Up Jumbo", 1900; MS002.001.014.00001 (Box 14)
    Elephants; Games; photographic print; Jumbo; Barnum, P. T. (Phineas Taylor)
    - Cut-up Jumbo jigsaw puzzle box lid, 1900; MS002.001.014.00001.00001; Thomson, Peter G. (Box 14)
      Forests; Elephants; Toys; photographic print; Jumbo
    - Cut-up Jumbo jigsaw puzzle assembled, 1900; MS002.001.014.00001.00002; Thomson, Peter G. (Box 14)
  - Books about Jumbo, 1935; MS002.001.015.00001 (Box 15)
    - Story of Jumbo book cover, 1935; MS002.001.015.00001.00001; Edwards, W.F.L. (Box 15)
      This book cover illustration is from W.F.L. Edwards, "The Story of Jumbo" (St. Thomas [Ont.]: Sutherland Press, c.1935).
      Elephants; Forests; Books; Jumbo
  - Broadside of Barnum's Museum Aquarial Gardens, 1862; MS002.001.016.00001 (Box Small Map Case 2 Drawer 5)
    Advertisements on both sides.
    Barnum, P. T. (Phineas Taylor)
  - Framed letter signed by P.T. Barnum, 1878; MS002.001.017.00001 (Box 17)
    Letter sent from P.T. Barnum to "Mercury" dated May 31, 1878. This framed letter was a gift to Tufts President Lawrence S. Bacow who transferred it to the archives.
  - "Baby Jumbo" Child's Toy, 1965 -- 1968; MS002.001.018.00001 (Box 18)
    Donated by Stephen Koob of the Corning Museum of Glass; Appears to be part of a Fisher Price Circus Wagon set (#900) from 1962.
  - "Jumbo the Elephant P.T. Barnum's Greatest Attraction" Plate, 1988; MS002.001.019.00001 (Box 19)
    Presented by Willitts Galleries, Painting by John Cargouet, Second in Circus Legends Series